Guide to the Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation oral histories 2008.030
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Vann, Albert, 2008 April 10; 2008.030.48
  Albert Vann was born in 1934 in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. At age eighteen, Vann joined the United States Marine Corps, eventually rising to the rank of sergeant. After leaving the military, Vann earned bachelor's and Toledo master's degrees in the field of education. Originally an educator, Vann's career has included service as both teacher and administrator in Brooklyn public schools, and founding of the African American Teachers Association. At the time of the 2008 interview, Vann was a member of the New York City Council, representing the 36th Council District (which includes parts of Bedford-Stuyvesant), and was a thirty-year Assemblyman of the New York City Council. A Democrat, Vann catalyzed two major court cases which helped to expand minority representation in New York government. He was also one of the founders of the City University of New York's Medgar Evers College.
  In this first of two interviews, Albert Vann details his early career as an educator, his start as a school teacher, and rise into administration. He describes his involvement in the "civil rights movement of education," founding the Negro Teacher's Association (now the African American Teacher's Association), organizing Black teachers, and involving parents. He discusses his personal political history, his relationship to Restoration as an elected official and community member, and funding sources and problems with funding. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Black nationalism |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Civil rights movements |z United States |y 20th century; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.) |x Social conditions; New York (State) |x Politics and government; United States |x History; Kennedy, Robert F.; New York (N.Y.). City Council; New York (State). Legislature; Thomas, Franklin A.; Vann, Albert
- Vann, Albert, 2008 April 22; 2008.030.49
  In this second of two interviews, Albert Vann recounts the 1960s-era Civil Rights Movement and his decision to found the Negro Teachers Association (now the African American Teachers Association). Vann remembers the founding of Restoration. He notes the institution's legacy programming; housing, social outreach, education, jobs training, and physical development services. Vann describes the 2008-era Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn as so entrenched in income inequality that it is almost "like two cities," and remarks on the difficulties of presiding over an area of distinct income inequality. Vann lists female political leaders who've influenced his life, details his start in politics, describes his electoral base, and comments on his first few years in elected office. At the interview's end, Vann provides some insight into his family's background and remarks on his personal life. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Civil rights movements |z United States |y 20th century; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New York (N.Y.) |x Social conditions; United States |x History; African-American Teachers Association; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); New York (State). Legislature; Richardson, Elsie; Vann, Albert
- Walsh, Robert, 2008 May 15; 2008.030.50
  Robert Walsh was born in 1959, one of seven children in the Bay Ridge neighborhood of Brooklyn. After an early childhood in the Bensonhurst neighborhood of Brooklyn, Walsh moved with his family to the small Upstate town of Amenia, in New York's Dutchess County. Walsh returned to New York City to attend Fordham University, where he received a bachelor's degree in political science and a Master's of Public Affairs, and began a career in public service. He worked in New York City mayor Ed Koch's administration from 1981 to 1989, which he left to lead the Union Square Partnership, a public-private business improvement collaboration credited for revitalizing the neighborhood. At the time of the interview, Walsh was the Commissioner of the New York City Department of Small Business Services (SBS), a position he took on in January 2002 and left in 2013. During his tenure, the SBS provided services for New York City's 220,000 small businesses.
  In this interview, Robert Walsh, then-Commissioner of the New York City Department of Small Business Services (SBS), discusses his personal history as a resident of Brooklyn and civil servant, noting biographer Jack Newfield's memoir of Robert Kennedy as particularly influential in Walsh's own life. He notes collaborative projects of the SBS and Restoration. Walsh notes past work experiences that prepared him for work in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, including his time leading the Union Square Partnership; and cites 2008-era evidence of revitalization, and says his role is to encourage entrepreneurship and public-private cooperation. He reflects on the sometimes tense relationship between urban renewal, gentrification, displacement, and affordable housing. Walsh discusses a number of public-sector vehicles for neighborhood improvement, including new market tax credits, subsidies, and capital investment. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Affordable housing; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Cultural facilities |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Enterprise zones |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Entrepreneurship |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Social justice |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban renewal |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Kennedy, Robert F.; New York (N.Y.). Department of Small Business Services; Walsh, Robert W.
- Watkins, Thomas H., 2008 January 29; 2008.030.51
  Thomas H. Watkins was born in 1927, in the New York metropolitan area, and moved with his family to the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn when Watkins was two years old. Watkins came from a politically interested family; his grandfather, the attorney Glen Jones, argued before Congress for federal protections for Black Americans from lynching. Watkins' career began at The New York Amsterdam News, the city's oldest Black newspaper. In 1952, Watkins founded his first weekly newspaper, the Afro Times. In 1972, Watkins founded his flagship paper, the New York Daily Challenge, a daily newspaper distributed city-wide, which was also New York City's first and only Black daily newspaper. The publication's corporate offices stood in Restoration Plaza, home of Restoration. An unabashed capitalist, Watkins founded the Daily Challenge as a way to route Black New Yorkers' newspaper monies into a paper owned by, written by, and catering to other Black New Yorkers.
  Thomas H. Watkins, founder, owner, and publisher of the New York Daily Challenge, begins this interview with a short history of each of his three newspapers. He shares his views on the value of entrepreneurship for Black residents of Brooklyn, including the power to uplift from poverty. He remembers the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn of his youth, noting the relationship between churches, education, and social mobility. Watkins discusses Bedford-Stuyvesant's history of community activism, and shares historical details from the actions of the Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council, the founding of Restoration, and the assassination of Robert F. Kennedy. He expounds upon the importance of First Amendment rights and press freedoms, and the relationship between marketing and the media. He shares his disdain for both public and parochial school systems, citing racism as one of its endemic problems. In conclusion, Watkins shares his prognosis of Restoration's legacy and his hopes for its future. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions; Business enterprises |x African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Civil rights movements |z United States |y 20th century; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Entrepreneurship |x African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Newspaper publishing |z New York (State) |z New York; Schools |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Daily Challenge, Inc; Kennedy, Robert F.; Richardson, Elsie; Watkins, Thomas H.
- Westbrooks, Aricka, 2008 April 15; 2008.030.52
  Aricka Westbrooks, born 1970, was the Chief Executive Officer and President of Jive Turkey, a quick-order restaurant that specialized in deep-fried turkey, located in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. At the time of the 2008 interview, the restaurant had been open for five years. Jive Turkey was Westbrooks' first business; prior to her entrance into entrepreneurship, she worked in fashion public relations. Westbrooks' business was enabled by support from Restoration's revolving loan capital fund. Westbrooks served on the board of the Myrtle Avenue Business Improvement District, and was active in the local merchants' association.
  In this interview, Aricka Westbrooks describes the process she went through to finance her quick order fried turkey restaurant, which was enabled through Restoration's revolving capital fund. She describes her current work as an entrepreneur, and imagines what she might have done if she hadn't received a Restoration small business loan. Interview conducted by Bahati Williams.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Entrepreneurship |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Fundraising |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Restaurants |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Westbrooks, Aricka
- Weston, Randy, 2008 January 22; 2008.030.53
  Randy Weston was born in New York City in 1926. A celebrated American jazz pianist, composer, and band leader, he grew up in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. After serving in the United States Army during World War II, Weston's jazz career took off as be began playing with national jazz figures. In 2001 he received a National Endowment for the Arts lifetime honor as a Jazz Master.
  In this interview, Randy Weston remembers his first performance at the Billie Holiday Theatre. He discusses the importance of music in African-American history. Weston recalls a number of influential musicians he has known and collaborated with throughout his life. He identifies several musicians and family members in a photograph, as well as a poster from a performance at the Billie Holiday Theatre. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Musicians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Popular music |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Weston, Randy
- Williams, David, 2008 May 12; 2008.030.54
  David Joseph Williams, aged eighteen, of the East Flatbush neighborhood of Brooklyn, had studied at Restoration's Youth Arts Academy since the age of five. An enthusiastic student of African drum teacher Delwyn Stanton-Gilkes, he performed throughout the five boroughs of New York City and in Guinea, West Africa. At the time of the 2008 interview, Williams was still attending drum class despite having passed the age limit in addition to being a student at Medgar Evers Middle College High School.
  In this short interview, David Williams describes his involvement with Restoration's Youth Arts Academy, where he is a student of African drums. Williams discusses the impact arts education has had on his life, and reflects on arts programming in general. He talks about changes he's seen in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn and recalls his move several miles south to East Flatbush. Interview conducted by Anasa Scott.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Music education; Musicians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Performing arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Brooklyn Academy of Music; Stanton-Gilkes, Delwyn; Williams, David Joseph; Youth Arts Academy
- Winborne, Wayne, 2008 January 16; 2008.030.55
  Wayne C. Winborne (born 1959) grew up in Portsmouth, Virginia to a father who worked in the shipyards, and was educated at Stanford University and New York University. After graduating college, Winborne moved to the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn to perform community development for inner-city youth. From his perch in Brooklyn, Winborne became involved with both Restoration and the Ford Foundation. In 2003, Winborne joined Restoration's Board of Directors. At the time of the 2008 interview, Winborne was the Chairman of the Board of Directors of Restoration and a vice president of business diversity outreach at Prudential Financial. In 2015, Winborne become the executive director of Rutgers University's Institute of Jazz Studies.
  Wayne C. Winborne begins this interview with a discussion of the socio-economic difficulties faced by inner-city African Americans, and reflects on the roles of economic development and cultural education in eradicating the cycle of poverty. Winborne describes his own ambitious youth; including his education at Stanford University and his move to Brooklyn, New York, where he developed youth programs. He details his path to serving as the Chairman of the Board of Directors of Restoration. Winborne describes cultural changes in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn since 1988, many of them ushered in by Restoration. Winborne speaks of an era of financial difficulty, and shares his views on necessary financial and programming measures. At the interview's end, Winborne lists members of Restoration's Board of Directors who have enriched his life, and expresses his enthusiasm for Restoration's next forty years. Interview conducted by Jako Borren.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Nonprofit organizations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Grannum, Colvin W.; Winborne, Wayne
- Young, Lester, Jr., 2008 January 31; 2008.030.56
  Dr. Lester Young, Jr., EdD, was a career educator born and raised in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. His professional experience includes time served as a teacher, guidance counselor, supervisor of special education, elementary school principal, and the Associate Commissioner with the New York State Education Department. At the time of the 2008 interview, Dr. Young was a visiting professor at Long Island University's Graduate School of Education and a contributor to Restoration.
  In this interview, Dr. Lester Young, Jr. discusses his current connection and involvement with Restoration and its role in the African-American civil rights movement. Young talks about housing affordability, gentrification, and his concerns for the future of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. He looks at the role of arts education in young peoples' lives. Young recalls his own public school education and his training as a young educator in Bedford-Stuyvesant. Young also speaks about school violence and solutions. He focuses on Restoration's roles in shutting down the "prison pipeline" for young Black men and enabling "total" human development; spanning jobs, arts, housing, education, and emotional maturity. He remembers the role his father, the famous jazz musician Lester Young, had on his life. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Civil rights movements |z United States |y 20th century; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community organizing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Education |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Educators |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Musicians; Theater |z New York (State) |z Kings County; United States |x History; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Billie Holiday Theatre; Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History; Young, Lester; Young, Lester, Jr., Dr.
- Restoration Homeowners, 2008 February 21; 2008.030.57
  Adrienne G. Haskell grew up in Queens, New York City. Restoration's mortgage lottery enabled Haskell to purchase her first home in March of 2007.
  Avery Beard is a school teacher who grew up in Washington, D.C. Restoration's mortgage program and Housing and Urban Development subsidies enabled Beard to purchase her first home.
  Dionne Wyckoff grew up on Manhattan's Upper West Side. She purchased her first home through Restoration's home ownership program.
  In this trio of interviews, three narrators who purchased their first homes with aid from Restoration's home ownership program discuss the process of purchasing their homes. They describe their neighborhood in Brooklyn as entering the beginning phases of gentrification. The narrators also discuss their relationship with Restoration. Interviews conducted by Bahati Williams.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Home ownership |x Social aspects |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation